First Methodist Church (Auburn, N.Y.) Records
First Methodist Church (Auburn, N.Y.) Records
1833-1969
3 reels microfilm.
Microfilm of 18 bound volumes and two folders of loose papers. Financial records, minutes, church history, record books, registers, and other church documents.
3166082
Biographical History
The First Methodist Church in Auburn, New York was organized in 1819. The church had several locations in Auburn: its first home was a wooden structure on Chapel Street in 1821, followed by a stone church in 1833 and a brick church on Exchange Street in 1869. The present (2010) location is the corner of South Street and Fitch Avenue, consecrated in 1957.
In 2008 the congregations of First Methodist and of Trinity United Methodist voted to merge the two bodies into the Auburn Methodist Church.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The First Methodist Church (Auburn, N.Y.) Records consists of three reels of microfilm representing 18 bound volumes and two folders of loose papers. The collection includes financial records, minutes, church history, record books, registers, and other church documents. The original material was in.
Arrangement of the Collection
Bound volumes are in chronological order. Two folders of loose papers appear at the end of Reel 3.
Related Material
has a number of collections relating to a number of churches in and around Central New York. Please refer to the for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; New York State; First Methodist Church (Auburn, N.Y.); Church records and registers.; Churches -- New York (State) -- Syracuse.; Methodist Church -- New York (State) -- History.; New York (State) -- Church history.; Church records.; Microfilms.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Unspecified, circa 1970.
Inventory
- Church records
  - Volume 1, 1844-1869 (Reel 1)
  - Volume 2, 1872-1885 (Reel 1)
  - Volume 3, 1885-1906 (Reel 1)
  - Volume 4, 1906-1935 (Reel 1)
  - Volume 5, 1832-1866 (Reel 1)
  - Volume 6, 1868-1901 (Reel 2)
  - Volume 7, 1908; 1850-1938 (Reel 2)
  - Volume 8, 1909-1919 (Reel 2)
  - Volume 9, 1819-1873 (Reel 2)
  - Volume 10, 1855-1877 (Reel 2)
  - Volume 11, 1887-1908 (Reel 2)
  - Volume 12, 1927-1940 (Reel 3)
  - Volume 13, 1940-1949 (Reel 3)
  - Volume 14, 1892-1903 (Reel 3)
  - Volume 15, 1903-1910 (Reel 3)
  - Volume 16, 1914-1927 (Reel 3)
  - Volume 17, 1927-1940 (Reel 3)
  - Volume 18, 1889-1908 (Reel 3)
  - Folders 1 and 2, 1833-1969 (Reel 3)
    Item 1: No. 42, History of First Methodist Church, Rev. John Alabaster, pastor 1879, 1879
    Item 2: No. 36, History of First United Methodist, Ralph C. Paul 1969-02-21, 21 Feb 1969
    Item 3: No. 35, Bank note of $8000, to be paid to James Hall 1839-01-22, 22 Jan 1839
    Item 4: No. 2, Indenture of the First Society of Methodist Episcopal Church, Talmadge Cherry, clerk 1833-02, Feb 1833
    Item 5: No. 23, Yesterday and Today church history, Harold George Stearns, pastor 1939-03-01, 1 Mar 1939
    Item 6: No. 44, An Historical and Pictorial Souvenir and History of the First Methodist 1911-05, May 1911
    Item 7: No. 139, The King's Daughters of the First Methodist Church constitution and minutes 1889-10-17, 17 Oct 1889
    Item 8: No. 123, Record of Women's Foreign Missionary Society of Auburn 1914/1927, 1914-1927
    Item 9: No. 134, Epworth League minutes of meetings and membership lists 1903-05-15/1910-10-14, 15 May 1903-14 oct 1910
    Item 10: No. 122, Offical Board of 1st M.E. Church record of meetings, Dr. Purington, Sec'y 1909/1919, 1909-1919
    Item 11: No. 130, Minutes of Sunday School board 1940-10-15/1948-09-26, 15 Oct 1940-26 Sep 1948
    Item 12: No. 129, Minutes of Sunday School board 1927-12-07/1940-09-17, 7 Dec 1927-17 Sep 1940
    Item 13: No. 196, Record book of first M.E. Church 1868/1899, 1868-1899
    Item 14: No. 197, General alphabetical register, marriages and baptisms 1861/1868, 1861-1868
    Item 15: No. 120, Minutes of Women's Missionary Society 1927-09/1940-06-12, Sep 1927-12 Jun 1940
    Item 16: No. 3, Record of stewards of the First Society of M.E. Church 1832-11-03/1866-09-17, 3 Nov 1832-17 Sep 1866
    Item 17: No. 119, Minutes of the North St. M.E. Sunday School 1855/1877, 1855-1877
    Item 18: No. 135, Board meeting minutes 1908/1938, 1908-1938
    Item 19: No. 121, Secretary's record book of Y.P.S.C.E. 1892-09-08/1902-09-17, 8 Sep 1892-17 Sep 1902
    Item 20: No. 205, Comprehensive Church Record of M.E., John C. Nichols, Pastor 1906-06-18, 18 Jun 1906
    Item 21: No. 198, Comprehensive Church Record 1885, 1885
    Item 22: No. 206, Church Record 1885/1906, 1885-1906